<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-01-26T00:53:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Overthinking</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/overthinking/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/overthinking/</id>
    <published>2014-01-26T00:53:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-01-26T12:04:51+08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;First published in my old website and reposted on &lt;a href="http://lifehacker.com/5899592/overthinking-and-your-child+like-mind"&gt;Lifehacker&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Overthinking puzzle" src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7435/12143175453_c73cb4a1b7_z.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Con­sider the ques­tion in the image above. I found this spread­ing on Face­book the other day and it took me a few min­utes to solve. Go on. Try. (If you want to know the answer. It’s at the end of the arti­cle.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you seen the Bollywood film 3 Idiots? It’s the highest-grossing Bol­ly­wood film of all time in India about the adven­tures of three col­lege engi­neer­ing stu­dents. One of the scenes left an impression on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="space pen" src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7305/12143613986_30f18aeeee_o.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="space pen" src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5527/12142958075_fc1907eebc_o.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="pencil" src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7378/12143203883_3699707dbc_o.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*Let me clar­ify that I am aware this space pen story is an urban myth. I am only using it as a sto­ry­telling device and for some humor (at least for me and the audi­ence in the the­atre who laughed at the scene). It made me think about how we over­think which led to this post. Whether it is true or not is besides the point.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the chil­dren we once were, grow­ing up was a process of becom­ing adults. Not only bio­log­i­cally but also men­tally. We learned to be respon­si­ble, to pay the bills, to get things done and we learned the com­plex world of adult­hood. To become adults we had to lose our tantrums, silli­ness, our child­hood. And we lost our minds. Our child-like minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mind of a child is the great­est gift we will ever receive. As embryos in our moth­ers’ womb, our heart, the first organ to develop only to power the next organ—the devel­op­ing brain which is soon mak­ing a quar­ter of a mil­lion new neu­rons every minute. In the first 10 years of life, our infant brain will have made bil­lions and bil­lions of con­nec­tions. It is a super­charged engine for learn­ing and cre­ativ­ity. Yet by adult­hood we have &lt;a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/ken_robinson_says_schools_kill_creativity.html"&gt;lost most of this creativity&lt;/a&gt;. We now think like adults. That is we think too much and our thoughts are too influ­enced by our knowl­edge. We need to get back our abil­ity to think like kids again. How?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where online would you find a lot of smart and knowl­edge­able peo­ple? Quora of course. I really like to visit Quora and learn from sub­ject mat­ter experts show­ing off their wits and exper­tise. Though some­times they over­think and com­pli­cate prob­lems with com­pli­cated answers. Many times peo­ple are just try­ing to show off how clever they are with rocket sci­ence. Like &lt;a href="http://www.quora.com/What-is-the-easiest-way-to-cut-a-pizza-into-11-equal-slices"&gt;this question&lt;/a&gt; on Quora.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Quora question" src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3732/12143449744_d1886c2cfd_o.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most pop­u­lar answer for the ques­tion before I answered involved cal­cu­la­tions with com­passes, con­cen­tric cir­cles, Pythagorean the­o­rem and square roots. I have no idea what a con­cen­tric cir­cle is, let alone cooks in a pizza kitchen. And who keeps com­passes in a kitchen? But since it’s the most pop­u­lar answer I sup­pose over­think­ing is pop­u­lar in Quora.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imag­ined myself with no math­e­mat­i­cal knowl­edge, a cook good with my hands, in a hot and humid kitchen faced with this prob­lem. What would I do? Turns out that the bet­ter solu­tion is much sim­pler and would only required a piece of string and a pen at the very least. Shouldn’t be too hard to find in a kitchen. And so I offered &lt;a href="http://www.quora.com/What-is-the-easiest-way-to-cut-a-pizza-into-11-equal-slices/answer/Aen-Tan"&gt;my answer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All you have to do is cir­cle a string around the pizza to cut a length equal to the pizza cir­cum­fer­ence. Then fash­ion a divider of some sort or even use your thumb and index fin­ger. Adjust your thumb and fin­ger and wrap the string eleven times equally around them. This effec­tively divides the string into eleven equal parts. Use a pen and mark the string. Cir­cle the string around the pizza again and cut using the mark­ings as guides. My answer received more than a hun­dred votes, went on to become the most voted and the ques­tion was made a &lt;em&gt;Best Source&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Solution" src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2890/12143753226_66a141e5eb_z.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Con­jur­ing com­plex math­e­mat­i­cal equa­tions may make you look smart but to become truly cre­ative you need to be able to lib­er­ate your mind from the the shell of knowl­edge, edu­ca­tion and adul­ti­fi­ca­tion you have accu­mu­lated. Only then can you think like a child again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="answer-to-the-numbers-question"&gt;Answer to the numbers question&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ques­tion has noth­ing to do with math­e­mat­ics. Look for the closed loops or shapes in each num­ber and count them. In 0, 6, 8 and 9. 8 has two of them. 2581 has two. The answer is 2.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Init</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/init/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/init/</id>
    <published>2014-01-25T15:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-01-26T00:44:40+08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s still January, not too late to add having a new blog to my resolutions. My last decently successful blog &lt;em&gt;aentan.com&lt;/em&gt; lasted just under three years. I made it to the Hacker News front page &lt;a href="https://www.hnsearch.com/search#request/all&amp;amp;amp;q=aentan.com&amp;amp;amp;sortby=points+desc"&gt;a couple of times&lt;/a&gt;, reposted an article to &lt;a href="http://lifehacker.com/5899592/overthinking-and-your-child+like-mind"&gt;Lifehacker&lt;/a&gt; and landed various job opportunities. Problem was… maintaining a WordPress site in a shared hosting environment is annoying. Dreamhost was a hundred bucks a year. Didn’t make sense anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to develop my own blog engine &lt;a href="http://writeonpure.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pure&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and wrote a couple of articles on it. It was an ambitious project in which articles are visually composed like Keynote or Powerpoint slides. It’s a Javascript monster. I spent a year developing it with my free time but it didn’t stick with me. I had to rely on a browser to write and I couldn’t easily write offline. Still feels like a lot of work. Putting Pure on Heroku is also expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here I am with a new setup. It’s much better and it’s free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="plumbing"&gt;Plumbing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I experimented with &lt;a href="http://jekyllrb.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jekyll&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and it wasn’t flexible enough for me. Then I discovered &lt;a href="http://middlemanapp.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Middleman&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Like Jekyll it’s a Ruby gem but much more flexible. It’s based on &lt;a href="http://www.sinatrarb.com"&gt;Sinatra&lt;/a&gt;, like a mini framework. I also get an asset pipeline which means I can serve minified and concatenated assets for better front-end performance. And since it’s a static site, there’s no server-side processing nor database and thus blazing fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m putting the entire blog and it’s content in a public &lt;a href="https://github.com/aentan/aenism"&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt; on Github. It makes sense because the content is public anyway. It also opens up the possibly of contributing articles by pull-request. Most important of all, Github is free. Github pages are served by Github’s CDN which wouldn’t have been trivial nor free to set up on my own hosting. Using a decentralized source-control system like Git means I’ll always have my blog and content backed up locally. Even if Github dies tomorrow (pretty unlikely) I can easily redeploy the site somewhere else like Heroku.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="frontend"&gt;Frontend&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Underneath the hood is &lt;a href="http://getbootstrap.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which makes the site adaptable to various devices and screen sizes. Blogs should be responsive. Reading Wordpress blogs isn’t so nice on mobile devices. Using plugins to make it work was so ugly I didn’t even bother to do it with my old blog. Bootstrap is a better way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides jQuery which is pretty much a standard for interactivity on most sites, I’m using &lt;a href="http://www.greensock.com/gsap-js/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;GSAP&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for animating the masthead. It’s 20× faster than jQuery and even faster than CSS3 animations and transitions. See the &lt;a href="http://www.greensock.com/js/speed.html"&gt;speed comparison&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve noticed the really fast loading of articles from the homepage, I’m using &lt;a href="http://pjax.heroku.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;pjax&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – a portmanteau of &lt;em&gt;pushState&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;ajax&lt;/em&gt;. Makes the site real snappy. I also added a fade transition between pages for elegance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="design"&gt;Design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though I didn’t continue using Pure I liked its simple content-centric design. Blogs are not marketing websites. The content should take center stage. Typography and whitespace are the chief elements of a good blog design. &lt;a href="https://medium.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Medium&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://alistapart.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;ALA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; embody this functional aesthetic well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The typeface is the modern &lt;em&gt;Proxima Nova&lt;/em&gt; for both headings and body text, implemented as a web font from &lt;a href="https://typekit.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Typekit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Proxima Nova was designed by &lt;a href="http://www.marksimonson.com/fonts/view/proxima-nova"&gt;Mark Simonson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The animated masthead at the top of the homepage represents my consciousness. It’s some of the things that have inspired me and defined me – books, films, music, favorite things, brands, possessions. They’d give you a good idea of the person I am. I created a script called &lt;em&gt;Bokeh&lt;/em&gt; and it uses GSAP for hardware-accelerated animation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Article pages are inspired by the simplicity of &lt;a href="http://medium.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Medium&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and simpler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="third-party-services"&gt;Third-party services&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of rolling my own commenting system, I rely on &lt;a href="http://disqus.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disqus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which has just the right features and looks good. Saves me time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover images are pulled directly from &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Flickr&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The images articles are also hosted in my personal Flickr photostream. First, Flickr already provides different sizes of each image which saves me the effort of resizing. Secondly it’s also a poor man’s CDN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about you? If you’ve done cool stuff with your blog or site please share by posting a comment.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
