<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-01-29T00:23:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>First contribution to Bootstrap</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/first-contribution-to-bootstrap/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/first-contribution-to-bootstrap/</id>
    <published>2014-01-29T00:23:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-01-29T09:10:03+08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href="https://github.com/twbs/bootstrap/pull/11536"&gt;first pull request&lt;/a&gt; for Bootstrap has been merged into master. Just some additional CSS to add previously unsupported button dropdowns to justified button groups. Here’s a demo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="100%" height="192" src="http://jsfiddle.net/5kFx6/3/embedded/result,html,css" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are using the latest &lt;a href="https://github.com/twbs/bootstrap"&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; (&amp;gt; v3.0.3) it has five lines of my code in it!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Child mind</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/child-mind/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/child-mind/</id>
    <published>2014-01-26T06:02:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-01-27T23:36:23+08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Con­sider this riddle I found spread­ing on Face­book some while ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This problem can be solved by children in five to ten minutes, programmers in an hour and people with higher education…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;table class="table table-bordered text-center"&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;8809 &amp;rarr; 6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;5555 &amp;rarr; 0 &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;7111 &amp;rarr; 0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;8193 &amp;rarr; 3&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;2172 &amp;rarr; 0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;8096 &amp;rarr; 5&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;6666 &amp;rarr; 4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1111 &amp;rarr; 0&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;3213 &amp;rarr; 0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;9999 &amp;rarr; 4&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;7662 &amp;rarr; 2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;7756 &amp;rarr; 1&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;9313 &amp;rarr; 1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;6855 &amp;rarr; 3&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0000 &amp;rarr; 4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;9881 &amp;rarr; 5&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;2222 &amp;rarr; 0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;5531 &amp;rarr; 0&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;3333 &amp;rarr; 0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2581 &amp;rarr; ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I solved it pretty quickly. Why don’t you try?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you seen the Bollywood film &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/3_Idiots"&gt;&lt;em&gt;3 Idiots&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;? Here’s the funny space pen scene from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="space pen" src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7305/12143613986_30f18aeeee_o.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="space pen" src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5527/12142958075_fc1907eebc_o.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="pencil" src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7378/12143203883_3699707dbc_o.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True story or not, this scene propones the folly of complex solutions to simple problems. How many times have we caught ourselves inventing space pens?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chil­dren we once were, grow­ing up was largely about maturing psychologically into adults. Respon­si­bility, paying the bills, getting things done and various complexities we call adult­hood. To come of age was to lose our tantrums, silli­ness and innocence. Hence started the displacement of our childly minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The artless mind of a child is our great­est gift. As embryos in our moth­ers, our heart is the first organ to develop only to power the next – the seedling brain which will eventually make a quar­ter of a mil­lion new neu­rons every minute. By the age of ten, each of us would have made bil­lions and bil­lions of neural con­nec­tions. It is a super­charged engine for learn­ing and cre­ativ­ity. Yet by adult­hood we would have &lt;a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/ken_robinson_says_schools_kill_creativity.html"&gt;displaced most of this creativity&lt;/a&gt;. The adult mind thinks too much. Its thoughts too influ­enced by knowl­edge. We must regain the ability to think like kids again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quora is a knowledgeable community. Admist the clever answers one often finds over­thinking and com­pli­cation from people triyng to look smart. &lt;a href="http://www.quora.com/What-is-the-easiest-way-to-cut-a-pizza-into-11-equal-slices"&gt;How would you cut a pizza into 11 pieces?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pop­u­lar answers to the ques­tion involved cal­cu­la­tions with com­passes, con­cen­tric cir­cles, Pythagorean the­o­rem and square roots until someone suggested &lt;a href="http://www.quora.com/What-is-the-easiest-way-to-cut-a-pizza-into-11-equal-slices/answer/Aen-Tan"&gt;a solution using strings&lt;/a&gt;, something not hard to find in a kitchen. I had no idea what a con­cen­tric cir­cle is, let alone pizza cooks. And who keeps com­passes in a kitchen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simple string solution involves first cir­cling then cutting a string around the pizza’s cir­cum­fer­ence. The string is then wrapped eleven times around one’s thumb and index finger until one gets eleven equal divisions by trial and error. The divisions are then marked. Cir­cle the string around the pizza again and cut from center to the markings. What simplicity! The answer soon became a rated as &lt;em&gt;best source&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Solution" src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2890/12143753226_66a141e5eb_z.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Con­jur­ing math­e­mat­i­cal mumbo jumbo may make one look smart. To be truly cre­ative one needs to be able to lib­er­ate the mind from accumulated grown-up banality. Only then the child mind re-emerges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="answer-to-the-numbers-question"&gt;Answer to the numbers question&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ques­tion has noth­ing to do with math­e­mat­ics. Look for the closed loops or shapes in each num­ber and count them. In 0, 6, 8 and 9. 8 has two of them. 2581 has two. The answer is 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;First published in my old website and reposted on &lt;a href="http://lifehacker.com/5899592/overthinking-and-your-child+like-mind"&gt;Lifehacker&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Init</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/init/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/init/</id>
    <published>2014-01-25T15:45:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-01-27T22:16:59+08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s still January, not too late to add having a new blog to my resolutions. My last decently successful blog &lt;em&gt;aentan.com&lt;/em&gt; lasted just under three years. I made it to the Hacker News front page &lt;a href="https://www.hnsearch.com/search#request/all&amp;amp;amp;q=aentan.com&amp;amp;amp;sortby=points+desc"&gt;a couple of times&lt;/a&gt;, reposted an article to &lt;a href="http://lifehacker.com/5899592/overthinking-and-your-child+like-mind"&gt;Lifehacker&lt;/a&gt; and landed various job opportunities. Problem was… maintaining a WordPress site in a shared hosting environment is annoying. Dreamhost was a hundred bucks a year. Didn’t make sense anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to develop my own blog engine &lt;a href="http://writeonpure.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pure&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and wrote a couple of articles on it. It was an ambitious project in which articles are visually composed like Keynote or Powerpoint slides. It’s a Javascript monster. I spent a year developing it with my free time but it didn’t stick with me. I had to rely on a browser to write and I couldn’t easily write offline. Still feels like a lot of work. Putting Pure on Heroku is also expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here I am with a new setup. It’s much better and it’s free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="plumbing"&gt;Plumbing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I experimented with &lt;a href="http://jekyllrb.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jekyll&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and it wasn’t flexible enough for me. Then I discovered &lt;a href="http://middlemanapp.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Middleman&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Like Jekyll it’s a Ruby gem but much more flexible. It’s based on &lt;a href="http://www.sinatrarb.com"&gt;Sinatra&lt;/a&gt;, like a mini framework. I also get an asset pipeline which means I can serve minified and concatenated assets for better front-end performance. And since it’s a static site, there’s no server-side processing nor database and thus blazing fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m putting the entire blog and it’s content in a public &lt;a href="https://github.com/aentan/aenism"&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt; on Github. It makes sense because the content is public anyway. It also opens up the possibly of contributing articles by pull-request. Most important of all, Github is free. Github pages are served by Github’s CDN which wouldn’t have been trivial nor free to set up on my own hosting. Using a decentralized source-control system like Git means I’ll always have my blog and content backed up locally. Even if Github dies tomorrow (pretty unlikely) I can easily redeploy the site somewhere else like Heroku.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="frontend"&gt;Frontend&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Underneath the hood is &lt;a href="http://getbootstrap.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which makes the site adaptable to various devices and screen sizes. Blogs should be responsive. Reading Wordpress blogs isn’t so nice on mobile devices. Using plugins to make it work was so ugly I didn’t even bother to do it with my old blog. Bootstrap is a better way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides jQuery which is pretty much a standard for interactivity on most sites, I’m using &lt;a href="http://www.greensock.com/gsap-js/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;GSAP&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for animating the masthead. It’s 20× faster than jQuery and even faster than CSS3 animations and transitions. See the &lt;a href="http://www.greensock.com/js/speed.html"&gt;speed comparison&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve noticed the really fast loading of articles from the homepage, I’m using &lt;a href="http://pjax.heroku.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;pjax&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – a portmanteau of &lt;em&gt;pushState&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;ajax&lt;/em&gt;. Makes the site real snappy. I also added a fade transition between pages for elegance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="design"&gt;Design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though I didn’t continue using Pure I liked its simple content-centric design. Blogs are not marketing websites. The content should take center stage. Typography and whitespace are the chief elements of a good blog design. &lt;a href="https://medium.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Medium&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://alistapart.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;ALA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; embody this functional aesthetic well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The typeface is the modern &lt;em&gt;Proxima Nova&lt;/em&gt; for both headings and body text, implemented as a web font from &lt;a href="https://typekit.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Typekit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Proxima Nova was designed by &lt;a href="http://www.marksimonson.com/fonts/view/proxima-nova"&gt;Mark Simonson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The animated masthead at the top of the homepage represents my consciousness. It’s some of the things that have inspired me and defined me – books, films, music, favorite things, brands, possessions. They’d give you a good idea of the person I am. I created a script called &lt;em&gt;Bokeh&lt;/em&gt; and it uses GSAP for hardware-accelerated animation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Article pages are inspired by the simplicity of &lt;a href="http://medium.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Medium&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and simpler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="third-party-services"&gt;Third-party services&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of rolling my own commenting system, I rely on &lt;a href="http://disqus.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disqus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which has just the right features and looks good. Saves me time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover images are pulled directly from &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Flickr&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The images articles are also hosted in my personal Flickr photostream. First, Flickr already provides different sizes of each image which saves me the effort of resizing. Secondly it’s also a poor man’s CDN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about you? If you’ve done cool stuff with your blog or site please share by posting a comment.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
